hello and welcome it's April 9th 2024
we're in active org stream
8.1 with Nathan Schneider discussing the
work in the book governable spaces so
there's many places we can enter in and
jump off from but first Nathan thank you
very much for joining and perhaps you
could say a quick hello and then we'll
jump into some quotes
yeah absolutely thank you for having me
it's wonderful to be
here okay so I have two quotes prepared
and then we'll also see any questions
people have from live chat or anything
else that comes up or anything you want
to ask all right so this is a quote on
page three of the book do you want to
say any words before the quote about
like what is this book about when did
you publish it how is it published who
did it Etc and then we'll jump in okay
sure yeah it's uh it was published in um
late February of this year 2024 and uh
with University of California press it's
available for free online as well as in
print um from you know wherever you get
books and um it's it's really an
exploration of the why the daily aspects
of our online lives and the governance
in those uh in our daily online lives
really matters um I've spent a lot of
years exploring like political economy
of online life trying to support the
development of alternative platforms
that are built as cooperatives and and
that sort of thing so I've worked a lot
with you know building things at the
company scale thinking about policy you
know found an accelerator for those
sorts of things um but in this one I I
kind of step back or step into you know
what is what are our political
experiences in everyday life life and
why do these matter and it kind of
starts with a history of how our our
online lives came to be structured and
managed the way they are and and then it
it blows up from there into um
suggesting that you know maybe some of
these these daily practices are actually
part of what's driving the kind of
Decline and crisis of democracy more
generally um and uh and then let's think
about what to do about it so it's it's
really a kind of plea for for um uh
recognizing the that um you know we
could do much more much better in
bringing democracy into the spaces that
we inhabit online and to recognize the
way in which we've you know often
without Rec without noticing it um
failed to do
that
awesome okay here's a quote on page
three and when I read it I thought about
active inference and about this
opportunity for a two-way street like
for people who are learning active
inference to hear about how the
perspectives that you're bringing and
drawing very richly on are just right up
even next to it so much of this book
dwells in interactions of human politics
and technological systems but as above
the more than human world envelops it
all providing the stage and the stakes a
planet waiting to see whether we can
govern our way out of self-d Destruction
deciding whether to maintain the
conditions necessary for human
civilization is there democracy in the
wild creatures hurdling through space on
a fragile world can expect no rights or
powers of decision from physics and
biology a government's claim to rule
means little in a high mountain
Wilderness or neighborhood whose
residents have made themselves
ungovernable to survive against a
hostile police force yet governance and
its cognates are names we use for doing
what all life forms must orchestrating
our perceptions and reactions so as to
have a chance at thriving in our
surroundings consider it simply the
intersection of power and cooperation an
intersection hardly unique to
us so what made you write
that um great great question um very a
very specific moment really um I was I
was um kind of early in imagining this
work that I've been doing for for some
years already forming into a book and I
was uh at a retreat um uh at a a
Catholic Retreat Center I go to
sometimes in Colorado and I was going on
a long walk and felt just like deeply
embarrassed actually for I've been doing
a lot of work around voting systems and
all this sort of stuff and um uh running
around with people developing like Dows
on block chains and all this and I was
just observing the interactions among
the creatures around me and um and just
recognizing like I I I just have to own
up to the fact that um first of all
governance is not something unique to
humans and um and and to kind of hold
the recognition that um you know that
the things that that this book is
engaging with
um
are are just all around us um and and to
connect this this question of democracy
in human societies with not to say that
democracy is what's happening in that
ecosystem but there is a form of
governance at work um and uh to to make
sure that those things aren't totally
separate um because I think we lose a
lot of our own potential when we when we
neglect that there are things going on
in the natural world and and we are the
natural world that um are beyond the the
systems that we've we've happened to to
dream up um so so to me it was really a
kind of passage of humility uh and I
really appreciate you lifting it up
because a lot of the rest of the book is
okay humans let's come together and
intentionally craft our governance
structures and all this sort of thing
but I think it's important to ground
that intentionality and that that that
um kind of literal construction of of um
you know our own political spaces in a
recognition that there's a much longer
story here and we're part of a much more
complex um set of systems and than you
know political science as a discipline
for instance tends to
appreciate that's awesome it's a similar
perspective like coming from a field
ecology View
we're always looking out seeing how
things are natured and patterned and
then people talk about governance or
regulation or even democracy like in the
Beehive or in the ant colony but also
it's a mapping it's like a metaphor it's
not intended to exactly describe what
ought to be the case for human systems
it is like the whole question of
biomimicry and there's a lot of like
biomaterials and bio
mimicry but then the question becomes
for the governance and interaction
systems like what can we learn from
what's quote
natural what is natural are computers
natural what do you
think well I I draw some on um on for
instance uh Adrien Marie Brown who uses
a lot of language about biomimicry she's
a activist and writer um Associated for
instance with like black lives matter
and
and um you know various kind of
Liberation movements today and she you
know she's not a scientist she's very
UPF friend about that but she draws a
lot on um the language and metaphors of
of um biomimicry and and related
discourses um to explain um to to
understand political change in in in our
world and and I I take a lot from her um
I I use her in some respects to deepen
and um correct for instance a thinker
like um Alexis toille who was a kind of
bounding figure in the theories of
democracy right who traveled around in
the in the early United States in the
1930s wrote Democracy in America the
kind of letter to the European
Aristocrats like himself about like how
this whole democracy thing was going and
what he emphasized was um this this
weird pattern which was that he just saw
the Civic associations and small um
ordinary practices of of democratic life
in people's communities and he saw this
as vital to the practice of larger scale
democracy and this is a a finding and
observation that's been reaffirmed in
later political Theory and and and
empirical political science um that um
healthy democracies at the level of a
nation state or a region um you know
really tend to to um have the these
kinds of thick textures uh of democratic
life in in their everyday environments
and and Adrian Marie Brown takes that
same idea but puts it in this kind of
biomimicry language this recognition of
the fractal the way in which um the
small is kind of uh in a system uh small
scales uh what what occurs at small
scales resembles what occurs at larger
scales um and to me is just an important
um lens through which to recognize
what's going on in our everyday online
lives has you know is affecting in ways
that are sometimes hard to perceive and
understand but that appear to be very
real affecting our ability to to
practice democracy uh at larger scal so
so um you know and I I think we have to
be we have we also have to be careful
about these kinds of these kinds of
inferences um but at the same time
democracy is such an imaginative
activity I mean it it it can only be
what we imagine it uh to be it can only
be what we let ourselves be what we let
ourselves practice and um therefore I
think the space of metaphor and and um
relationship is really important in
constructing our political lives we map
ourselves on to is uh vital and this is
also in the context of human societies
one one uh a project that I explore some
in the book that's still quite
preliminary is this idea of governance
archaeology I've been working on with
bica
carugati um who's a political scientist
um and um and what we've been exploring
is how to broaden the repertoire of of
governance histories that we can draw on
by building you know databases and
repositories of these histories um to
catalog what has has and does go on in
our world thinking about the way in
which for instance the so-called
founding fathers of the United States
for instance had they were reading books
about often ancient Greece and Rome
right and they were often referring to
those while they were justifying the
possibility of building a new kind of
democracy um and uh and that makes me
wonder what repertoire what histories
are we turning to today as we for
instance design the the flows of power
in online life or in other kinds of
spaces around you know addressing
climate change or uh governing undersea
cables or governing AI what metaphors
are we going to draw and what what um
playbooks are we going to turn to and if
we are able to allow ourselves to um
consider biomimicry to um um to consider
indigenous practices that have been so
often suppressed or neglected by
dominant Powers um if we allow ourselves
to um have some humility for instance
about those Colonial histories we've
been we've been told and we've often
integrated into our own self-
understanding you know suddenly our the
range of motion becomes broader this the
range of possibilities of what we could
do become broader and and essential
critique for in online spaces is just
like we've limited ourselves with a very
very profound um set of constraints a
design pattern I call implicit feudalism
you know the admins the mods telling
every you know having all the
power uh addressing problems through
censorship and Exile um you know this
the these things that we're very used to
in online spaces are actually a very
small subset of the possibilities of how
humans could could could interact
yeah thanks for adding all that I really
like the biological thread and the
naturalizing of the decision- making and
like the different perspectives that are
involved in that it was focused on the
human and the anthropological but also
like you mentioned uh in that first
quote like we're also dealing with
governance spaces that don't only
include humans as if that wasn't already
like a totally broad enough space um
and then the bottom up and the top down
is often how it's explored like from a
multiscale biological system's view
looking at multiscale governance or
regulation like of tissue
homeostasis and then that's kind of the
discussion is about the bottom up
signaling and the top down influences
and people who kind of favor one of
those accounts like the bottom up being
kind of explaining things in a sense by
their lower components but also giving
those lower components agency um so it's
just very interesting as we develop
like the particular works that connect
the systems and the broader perspectives
on human systems helping us see on one
hand the similarities that help make
biomimicry
plausible however it's not going to
provide any answers it's only going to
provide us kind of the the path or the
tool to to get up to a very challenging
human point which is like well then how
do we want the online governance to be
if not the Linux kernel or Reddit or
social media platform model so how have
you kind of explored that with medov and
elsewhere um just for context for those
who aren't familiar medov is an
organization that we you know we met
through I as I recall um and uh it's a a
network of people working around online
governance and this community has been
really Central to for me and writing
this book and then doing this work um
and um and one of the founding ideas
that we um a group of us developed as
metago was coming into being was um this
idea of modular politics um which is a
language just for imagining a different
texture a different framework for um for
online spaces um so today we tend to
assume okay you start a Facebook group
or you start a a a group chat or
whatever platform it is whoever starts
it has essentially all the power and um
they can delegate some of that power but
you know it all kind of comes from them
and it's it's not changeable it's it's
um kind of crude um and it's built on
this logic of uh the early ass online
communities which were like you know a
BBS server a bolet and board system like
sitting in somebody's house and the
people who logged in were guests in that
person's house and so yeah they had all
the power um but is that really does
that model describe the kinds of
communities that we're working with now
I don't think so I think for many of
them you know we could imagine some
really different kinds of of structures
and um the idea with modular politics is
rather than when you start a new
community you you just kind of fall into
this default implicit feudalism design
instead you have the ability to actually
design using assembling modules um the
kind of governance that you want so
assembling using um a kind of a a conect
collection of of tools that you choose
um you can try to capture the most
appropriate um uh governance for the
kind of space that that you're building
um and uh you know all this is to say I
mean in some ways it's all about just
like catching up to existing
organizations um where you know you can
write bylaws in a lot of different ways
and we need I think a kind of digital
equivalent uh to that that option to be
able to um really Define and and reflect
on what do we need in a given space is
this space something where I can vote
the mod out if I don't like what they're
doing or is it one where there's a jury
that makes decisions where people get
randomly selected um there are all kinds
of um ways you could imagine online
spaces being governed and um we just
really haven't had the chance to do that
there are a few exceptions that that I
look at that show that this approach is
not crazy because whenever people do
actually have the opportunity to
self-govern in digital space they end up
going this kind of Route so for instance
um when the city of Barcelona said hey
we want to support a whole lot more um
citizen
participation um and they helped develop
this platform called deum uh then
actually what did they do people started
building a bunch of modules for that
system they they built the system so
they could handle you know people
essentially writing plugins kind of like
plugins for a WordPress website except
in this case they're like
decision-making tools that you can add
and and you can pick and choose which
ones you want to use in the system and
um in this case it's less for the
platform than for the city but still
when you have that invitation to say how
could we self-govern uh uh suddenly
people get really creative about what
they um what they build uh another
context where this has occurred is is in
the context of blockchains um where um
uh this is a network design that unlike
the server based logic of earlier
internet Technologies the uh network is
uh governed across servers whether
you're talking about Bitcoin being
governed by miners or ethereum by
stakers or a dow like an organization on
say ethereum uh governed by token
holders in each case there is governance
is a problem in crypto context in a way
that it really hasn't been in other web
contexts regardless of you know this is
all in the context of lots of scams and
you know alant and all this stuff that
that we all know about but but this
nevertheless has produced um really the
first explosion of innovation in
governance technology for the internet
just because it's really the first time
people have had to figure this out and
there's been billions of dollars at
stake in how you self C these these
networks um and if you look at the
popular tools for instance for
developing Dows like Aragon for instance
um uh they have adopted essentially a a
modular structure um where you have a
kind of base layer and you can assemble
you know or the nosis system um you can
assemble different um uh modules for how
you want to self-govern and and um you
know build your community stepwise like
that um so so you know that we could
allow ourselves this tremendous
creativity uh that we've seen in these
little pockets where people have had the
opportunity to self-govern online
suddenly they start really going crazy
and coming up with some some really
really interesting designs um and uh uh
but in most of our online lives that is
not even an opportunity so the question
hasn't really Arisen for for so many
people great all right I'll ask some
questions from the live chat so two
questions from Sid feel free just to
answer however you want is it Democratic
if the community admin makes everyone in
the group an admin what is the
equivalent of a democratic space in a
telegram or Facebook community and
another related question what are some
affordances in modern online communities
that allow for governable
spaces okay great um let's see maybe
I'll start with the second one you know
what are some affordances you know in
the in the current context that we see
um you know uh one thing you I I found
is that trying to bring democracy into
particular spaces um for instance like
um I co-founded a Mastadon server called
social. Coop um it took a lot of work to
to build in uh Dem Democratic structures
we have to go to a separate platform
lumio to do decision-making we have a
separate platform awiki for managing our
bylaws and and the kind of how-to guides
and all those sorts of things um the
Mastadon did not um allow us to do a lot
um just by default built into the tool
but the fact that it's a Federated
Network that is small enough that a
group of people can download it run it
on a server and start trying to figure
out how to govern it that's a powerful
affordance um you know subreddits have a
lot of group autonomy they're able to
build at least you know significant
group Culture even though they rely on a
lot on admins and mods um and um and I
think reddits strengths really
demonstrate the power of community
self-governance um and and how much more
could be possible um the uh and so these
communities that allow uh these
platforms I mean that allow um kind of
distinct communities to form um and to
have real autonomy that's an important
prerequisite but it's really not
sufficient um and um and in terms of
what you can do with those tools you're
often working against them you're often
kind of bending over backwards to try to
get tools not designed for democracy to
work that way for instance like giving
everyone admin Authority I don't know
like that's kind of like giving
everybody the nuclear football you know
that's um that's not necessarily what a
lot of us would recognize is democracy
that's kind of like crazy um right um
it's it allows everybody to act and do
whatever where they want without
necessarily having structural
accountability to others and um the fact
that that feels like the best option or
the closest thing is just another
reminder of how poorly equipped these
tools are um so for instance what if
there were functionality built in where
you could say okay you know if a if an
admin starts really like going off the
rails the the participants maybe the
people with enough reputation in the
community you know who've who've been
upvoted a certain number of times like
can vote that person out of that role
and vote somebody new in um or you know
there a l wide range of structures one
could incorporate there could be a
petition system there could be a jury
system there could be you know votes
that are kind of ongoing uh ra uh rather
than just at one time um when you look
at for instance the the world of crypto
despite you know and you see through all
the scams and nonsense you know there's
actually been a ton of creativity and
okay how do we get decision-making
structures that actually reflect what
we're trying to do and and they're
continually iterating on this um in in
that context and and increasingly also
using the kind of biomimicry um but it
requires designing these these systems
differently um in the context where we
have um had kind of exceptions that
prove the rule like the Debian project
um uh or the transition of Debian is a
kind of operating system based on Linux
um it's run as like a direct as a
constitutional democracy that took a lot
of work to build in if you download
Wikipedia or sorry mediawiki the
software underlying Wikipedia it's all
the same software but you you start to
realize it doesn't have any of the the
cool governance structures that make
Wikipedia great built in you know those
are things that had to be added on top
built on kind of at the cultural layer
um and what would it look like to have
um to have tools that that were more set
up to enable people to have appropriate
and diverse kinds of of governance
structures built into their into their
tools right now if you want you know to
practice democracy if you want to do
things that are kind of recognizably De
Democratic online you have to really
bend over backwards you have to really
really work against the biases of the
system in order to get what you want uh
what I hope for is a world where you
know as the the um poet uh Peter Lauren
um Peter Moren put it you know a world
where it's easier to be good where you
know the default settings are a little
closer to the values that we claim to
hold about you know how Civic life
should
proceed great thank you all right some
questions from love evolve what are the
patterns of governable spaces and please
contrast physical governable spaces with
digital SL virtual governable
spaces yeah that's a good question in
terms of patterns um one tool that my
lab has built is called Community rule
it's a very
prototype uh platform Community rule.
info that uh enables people to like
author simple bylaws and we have some
templates built in um we turned them
into a book as well um the templates are
really um you know they're things like
um an elected board a jury petitions um
consensus docracy all these things are
practices that exist offline as well as
online in some contexts um and in some
respects I think of the challenge as
like catching online spaces back up to
what we've been doing offline um you
know I at the beginning of the book I
compare a mailing list I was running to
my mother's Garden Club and the Garden
Club had much better governance stoling
than the mailing list um but um but at
the same time I think when you look at
what people are doing in online cont
context um where self-governance has
really been taking off you see
possibilities of things Way Beyond what
we um we do in offline spaces or at
least just very different so for
instance in those crypto contexts I was
talking about you know often you're
dealing with Anonymous users you're
dealing with um uh uh you you can't rely
on a court system to you know address
wrongdoing you have to design structures
in a way that is kind of foreign to say
running a Bowling Club right because the
Bowling Club is able to build on a lot
of infrastructure of like the nation
state and law and courts and police and
all these things that can be used to
prevent wrongdoing um and in the context
of network native organizations that
aren't dependent on a on a nation state
and all these things um uh you need to
design governance around that you need
to make sure that that you know uh uh
people can there are consequences for
negative action you know for harmful
actions um and so it invites a different
kind of design a lot of the crypto um uh
uh uh governance designs have involved
some blend between like Financial stake
and personhood um uh and uh attempts to
um build in this combination of like
cryptography to secure a network and
um and economic incentives um you know
we would probably uh uh react really you
know Vis early to the idea of economic
incentives in like voting for a
president um but in the context of a of
an online Network it might make more
sense because we don't have like the
infrastructure of citizenship and we
don't have all these these other things
and maybe we don't want those things
right because you know those things are
protected by violent borders right and
we want to create online networks that
are more inclusive than than our nation
states maybe um so so you know to me
that is just thrilling and and part of
what
motivated um you know the at the heart
of what motivated me to write this book
as with like my last few books um you
know earlier one on the Cooperative
movement and then the one before that on
on Occupy Wall Street and the the
movements of 2011 was just like the
thrill at seeing people reinvent
democracy in real time um that to me is
I just love seeing that happen and and I
just fall in love every time I
experience it um and in some of these
online spaces I have seen that happen
I've seen people go back to the drawing
board and ask no wait what would we
actually want this structure to be set
up as um how would we actually want to
self-govern and they make all kinds of
mistakes and it's like embarrassing to
watch and all these things just like
like watching a social movement form is
kind of cringy constantly um but still
you have this feeling like this is this
process is alive you know we are
learning something new and um It's that
kind of moment that I hope more people
can can somehow
experience wow very
cool what about the art in the book or
perhaps more broadly how do you you see
visualizations and art and Aesthetics
and governance yeah thanks for asking
that um so I um uh turned to um a
collaborator I've worked with before
including on the governance archaeology
project I mentioned um Daria medic who's
a really brilliant artist and and um
digital rights activist um and uh and
you know to me the I've always been
really interested in the visual quality
of books in my lab does a lot of like
really um you know art heavy Productions
um and uh you know I think the word
words and images are you know produce an
important dialogue in particular I was
interested in how to represent
interfaces for this book um and if you
look at you know the normal way of doing
this is okay you do something on a web
browser and you take a screenshot and I
I I did that initially I I had a bunch
of screenshots and I when I looked at
them I thought you know it's not really
clear here what is going
on like um uh uh for the user in a kind
of visceral way um you know what's going
on phenomenologically like what what
what does this interface feel like it
doesn't translate in a screenshot when
we're moving our way through online
space and we're we're manipulating a you
know a mouse and a keyboard or or or or
we're using our fingers or we're we're
manipulating the space we see it really
differently than just like looking at a
screen or looking at a page um and in
order to show the the aliveness of these
spaces I thought okay we for this book I
really want to not just rely on those
screenshots but I want to uh create um
illustrations that um surface and and um
bring forward the the significant parts
of the interfaces I'm trying to
highlight um and that and that reveal
something about what using them might be
like and and um you know Daria is
someone who I you know I just really
appreciate her uh recognition of that
Vision she also has we did this work in
um in the you know during weekends on
the at the media archaeology lab which
is a lab here on campus that's a
basement full of old computers that work
and um and so we were kind of surrounded
by these retro interfaces and um and you
know built the illustrations um in that
in that way um you know also it was
important to rec you know when you look
at a book that's like 10 years old about
the internet and you look through the
screenshots that are that are depicted
in it and they all look like old and you
know kind of it makes the book age more
of interfaces drawing on kind of 80s
Aesthetics and things like
that that's great um like to kind of
represent that and the darker and the
lighter the the the the negative and the
positive like Visions for the interface
like in figure three it's the admin
options and there's the create rules
there's so many options to create rules
there's no um opportunity to ask what
people feel like and then you can just
jump down the Wormhole with getting
started before even creating a rule
that's kind of like nudge and then like
contrasting with figure eight where it's
like these overlapping overlays
Community fridge library for all
transformative Justice Center and then
at in the intersection of these multiple
layers and function there's more like a
neighborhood but one of those might
extend beyond the neighborhood but then
it's not as rich as like when it's
overlapping yeah no it it's um you know
and she she also
Incorporated these these um kind of
natural textures there are like fractal
images there there are roots and and um
you know the the goal was to um
recognize the way in which we are always
approaching interfaces through metaphors
um we are I mean going back to like the
names of interface designs like window
and I mean the Mouse um pointer
everything is a metaphor to something
else you know in crypto wallet um and
and coin token all every piece of
language that we use to describe our
online lives are full of metaphors to
earlier regimes of of manipulation and
design and and and power and um so we
tried to capture you know not only the
literal buttons and so forth on the
interface but also like what is the what
is the um metaphor going through here um
you know I thought about a lot like the
early online services like geoc cities
or um or uh there was uh eworld uh from
Apple which like imagine the internet is
like a city where you're going from
building to building geoc cities was
like you're you're in different cities
different districts um and I think those
early those early experiments with
language around the internet were really
important in terms of like helping
people imagine what was going on here
and um I wanted to make sure that those
metaphors were very present because
that's exactly kind of the thrust of the
book that these experiences of
interfaces we have are not just are not
just some kind of mundane thing
technical thing we have to work with
they actually are shaping our our
political imaginations in really
fundamental
ways that's awesome like a ballot or a
request for information is more than the
paper it's printed on it's different
than it has causal efficacy in the real
system that people are in so now to a
quote from page 129 near the end and
then there's also like 50 pages of
citations and index so that was very
cool this section on 129 I think book
ends shortly where as there's many
powerful pieces in this last section but
on 129 says implicit feudalism has been
a kind of meta governance and like so
much meta governance it too often hides
beneath notice but changing how we
govern requires being attentive to the
Met governance at work shaping the
background conditions of governance is
itself a form of governance so what
about that quote how is it related to
attention and perception and action and
all of that well when I W when we
started this organization The Meta metag
governance project which had already
been named when I got involved um I
didn't I hadn't come across that term it
just kind of s cool because for some
reason these days attaching meta to
anything sounds cool you know to some
people and um uh and uh then I realized
really through collaborators in that
Community um um that oh this is actually
a term that like political scientists
have developed and um and and and that
just helped me understand all the more
what we were up to um what this this
concept of meta governance came from was
the recogition that okay if you look at
the global order you know of like
governments and Nos and all these things
um there are there are the structures in
place like the government of Egypt but
then there's also the meta structures
that say okay here are the constraints
in which the government of Egypt is
going to exist um uh this is these are
the the structures within which NGS
operate um like for instance the
government of Egypt is essentially a
military dictatorship but you know there
there are a bunch of reasons why it kind
of makes sense to make it at least look
like it's a constitutional democracy
with a president right you know and
that's the nomenclature that get that
gets used because it's it creates a kind
of compatibility with the global
community and creates this this kind of
perception and this this set of this
kind of plausible deniability um and
that there is a kind of meta order
underlying what is possible I mean even
the idea of West Fan Nation States the
idea of like governments with a monopoly
over land within certain specified
borders is a form of meta governance at
the end of the book I point to this
wonderful website native um hyphen land.
CA that that um Maps indigenous
territories and they're overlapping you
know I live on the land of the um
principally arapo cheyen and ute people
they torically have shared this land um
used it in different ways and used it in
a migratory fashion and um you know they
they were not they didn't claim a kind
of Monopoly over it um and so there are
other ways of ordering our our
government systems and um and and and
and what starts as kind of like a
quibble about user interface design at
the beginning of the book ends with this
whole question about like hey you know
could have a very different way of
understanding how we self how we govern
ourselves um when because actually in
order to get to this interface design
question we have to start thinking about
the meta governance have to start
thinking about what is the underlying
set of rules that um constrain and
Define the possible set of rules um and
once we start messing with that meta
governance o a lot of things start start
opening up a lot of um pretty radical
possibilities and and I do hold out a
kind of you know I I I'm a media studies
Professor so I have to be cynical and
about most things but you know I do kind
of hold out a kind of um hope in like
some of the early dreams of the internet
which is to create a world where people
can connect across borders where um
where Geographic accidents of birth and
so forth are less important and people
can find people and their communities
regardless of you know where they come
from and and and and what they look like
and and all these sorts of things and um
you know I think now the question is is
more like how can we rather than say
regardless how can we live in where we
are be hold our identities our multiple
forms of identity um and also connect
with each other through you know as like
true peers in across our the network
that we have and um you know I in order
to really make good on that promise you
know I think we we need to revise the
kind of metag governance of online life
and and imagine what it means to be a
kind of true citizen um truly empowered
with you know the right to covern um in
these online spaces um rather than
simply deferring to what I think are in
many respects like deeply dangerous and
failed you know state-based institutions
or corporations to you know to run these
things for
us awesome thank you all right in our
last minute some more questions love
evolve writes pair of questions thoughts
on the metaphor of community garden and
more so gardening verb analogy to Shared
governing digital spaces question and
thoughts on citizen assemblies and their
rise in localities along with online
tools and platforms to support these
yeah thank you you um uh yeah the the
garden metaphor is is really present I
hope throughout um you know the book
starts out with with a kind of with a
picnic in a park that I imagined as
Prospect Park in New York City um and
talks about my mother's Garden Club um I
think the that you know I don't think I
I I have done the the my best thinking
around like that that um you know
deepening that set of relationships
between human political governance and
broader ecologies there's so much more
to be done and there's so much more that
others have done I just wanted to make
sure to have the nods in there you know
to have that th those Place uh you know
to to those kind of bookmarks to say
okay you know let's not forget we're
part of a broader ecology let's not
forget that humans are not you know the
only things managing resources on this
Earth um and um and so so I hope that
those nods um uh uh just at least um uh
uh convey some recognition that you know
for the limitations of so much else
that's in this B book and my thinking um
let's see the the other question was oh
was around citizens assemblies um I
think this is a really important opening
um I hope everybody you know learns
about it um and follows what's going on
in many part parts of the world in in um
Africa and South America and Europe um
in particular and um Canada has been
experimenting with these um we're
starting to get some exploration in the
US the idea here is is to um uh to to
develop structures alongside or instead
of um representative elections to
instead have randomly selected citizens
uh making decisions um uh or at least
developing
proposals um so you know for instance
this could look like um a government
saying okay we're kind of stuck on this
issue of how to address climate change
this is the you know what the government
of France has done and so we're going to
have an assembly to come together and
develop a new set of solutions that we
could potentially adopt um there's some
controversy in this in this scene of
people doing this stuff around should we
make these Buy ing um I'm personally in
favor of that I think we need to um have
you know essentially new channels for
you know shaping our societies and this
is a really powerful way we could do
that to to really work against the bias
of who ends up being a politician which
is like somebody who thinks they should
be a politician right um a lot of the
people who I trust most in my life are
the people who don't want a lot of power
you know um who aren't motivated by
seeking and retaining power um and so I
would love to see those people have
actually more power in our world um and
this kind of assembly uh process is a
way of achieving that um I I think that
these experiments have been extremely
promising there are some pretty cool
ways in which people are now
incorporating Ai and other Technologies
like with platforms like polus um and
and others there's an experiment going
on in MIT right now around this um
around integrating AI with citizen
assembly model um I've been advocating
for that with my own city government um
trying to identify ways in which we
could um we could use assemblies and
other processes like this to to solve
some of our kind of most polarized um
challenges but to me this is just one
example of of what we could explore if
we allowed oursel to recognize that
democracy is not just a set of fixed
institutions that we have to defend
against like authoritarians but actually
the democracy is an ongoing process that
we constantly have to be Reinventing
that was something Alexis daville
recognized that that WB Deo recognized
that that you know um I think just runs
you know it's it's it's a it's a deep
part of this democratic tradition and
something that is really being forgotten
today um you know I just plea that you
know the best defense is offense the
best the only way to to help democracy
um Thrive as a as a practice and vision
is is to keep Reinventing it um and to
enable it to
evolve thank you that really resonates
with a lot of the discussion in autop
poesis and self reconstitution and
regeneration within biological systems
and that is kind of
the naturalizing and the biopolitics of
cyberphysical systems
which is a novel Niche to be in so in
the last minutes what is metov SL your
lab and your research going to be
working towards how can people like
learn more and do more and
differently yeah so um medov is a
community that um is open and and uh on
a good day welcoming um that um I really
invite folks who are interested in this
conversation to to join you can find
more information at metag of.org um it a
lot of the community lives in a slack um
so unfortunately participation generally
involves joining that but we've got a
bunch of different research projects
going on as well as kind of community
Explorations um I recently finished
drafting a paper with some folks in that
community on attention economies and
governance design um exploring how to
how to make those fit together um
there's work on public AI um you know
rethinking the political economy of AI
there's work on um rethinking uh you
know the governance of philanthropy and
Grant making um so there a bunch of
lines of work that are going on there um
and my lab is the media economies Design
Lab at CU Boulder um I primarily work
with um graduate students here so if
you're interested in doing uh you know
especially Masters or PhD work uh on um
uh around issues like Democratic
economies or online governance um I'd
love to love to talk with
you all right thank you very much for
the work and for doing all this
cool projects and more so till next time
thank you Nathan absolutely such a
pleasure to be on here thank you peace
bye
e